<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zheln</title>
    <description>Weekly updates on high-quality and impactful health research. Methods: https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb</description>
    <link>https://zheln.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://zheln.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 16:25:55 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 16:25:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Power of Human Touch</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;gentle-touch-shown-to-reduce-pain&quot;&gt;Gentle touch shown to reduce pain.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;newborns-suffer-from-airway-suctioning-but-careful-positioning-is-likely-to-help&quot;&gt;Newborns suffer from airway suctioning, but careful positioning is likely to help.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2024-02-02-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;An image of a newborn, with an adult’s hand gently bending the newborn’s legs. This positioning technique is called facilitated tucking. Image credit: Kucukoglu S, Kurt S, Aytekin A. Ital J Pediatr. 2015;41:61. doi: 10.1186/s13052-015-0168-9. License: CC BY 4.0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-facts&quot;&gt;The Facts:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cochrane &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cochrane.org/CD013353/NEONATAL_medicine-free-management-neonates-pain-during-endotracheal-suctioning&quot;&gt;presented&lt;/a&gt; a study of a painful medical procedure in neonates. Many newborns, particularly preterm, cannot breathe very well, so a common procedure, so-called endotracheal suctioning, involves clearing their airways by sucking excessive secretions into a catheter. And, it’s known to be painful, so the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.cd013353.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Pirlotte S, Beeckman K, Ooms I, Cools F. Non-pharmacological interventions for the prevention of pain during endotracheal suctioning in ventilated neonates. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2024 Jan 18;1(1):CD013353. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD013353.pub2. PMID: 38235838; PMCID: PMC10795104.&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt; looked at what can be done to alleviate suffering, apart from the obvious medications – painkillers and anesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After analyzing data from 148 neonatal intensive care unit (ICU) patients across four randomized trials, the researchers were moderately certain that so-called facilitated tucking reduces suction-associated pain in neonates on mechanical ventilation. Facilitated tucking is a positioning technique that involves gently bending a baby’s arms and legs, as shown in the image above. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/pch/9.suppl_a.44aa&quot; title=&quot;Shah V, Ipp M, Sam J, Einarson T, Taddio A. Eliciting the minimal clinically important difference in the pain response from parents of newborn infants and nurses. Paediatrics &amp;amp; Child Health. 2004 May 1;9(suppl_a):44A-44A. doi: 10.1093/pch/9.suppl_a.44aa.&quot;&gt;13–20% change&lt;/a&gt; on the pain scale used in these trials is likely to be noticed by health care workers and caregivers alike, and facilitated tucking produced a 14–40% change. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s40138-016-0089-y&quot; title=&quot;Witt N, Coynor S, Edwards C, Bradshaw H. A Guide to Pain Assessment and Management in the Neonate. Curr Emerg Hosp Med Rep. 2016;4:1-10. doi: 10.1007/s40138-016-0089-y. Epub 2016 Mar 12. PMID: 27073748; PMCID: PMC4819510.&quot;&gt;several instruments&lt;/a&gt; for pain assessment in infants, and the one used here, Premature Infant Pain Profile, derives its scoring points from observing the baby’s facial actions, heart rate, and oxygen saturation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When planning their study, the authors wanted to assess all kinds of non-pharmaceutical treatments, including rocking the baby, skin-to-skin contact, or breastfeeding. It turned out that only gentle touch techniques were appropriately studied in the suctioning context. The researchers also wanted to assess a variety of outcomes, including mortality, nausea, vomiting, or intracranial hemorrhage but ended up looking at just the pain scores because these other outcomes were not reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uneasy side of medicine is that treating hurts sometimes. When it comes to children, pain is a particularly sensitive issue. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/archpedi.157.11.1058&quot; title=&quot;Simons SH, van Dijk M, Anand KS, Roofthooft D, van Lingen RA, Tibboel D. Do we still hurt newborn babies? A prospective study of procedural pain and analgesia in neonates. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2003 Nov;157(11):1058-64. doi: 10.1001/archpedi.157.11.1058. PMID: 14609893.&quot;&gt;uncomfortable truth&lt;/a&gt; is that newborn babies experience pain from medical procedures, too. Even worse – that pain is &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41390-019-0744-6&quot; title=&quot;McPherson C, Miller SP, El-Dib M, Massaro AN, Inder TE. The influence of pain, agitation, and their management on the immature brain. Pediatr Res. 2020 Aug;88(2):168-175. doi: 10.1038/s41390-019-0744-6. Epub 2020 Jan 2. PMID: 31896130; PMCID: PMC7223850.&quot;&gt;theorized&lt;/a&gt; to have an immense impact on brain development, potentially leading to devastating consequences. The new evidence concerning facilitated tucking and windpipe suctioning shows us just how much a gentle human touch can matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evidence&quot;&gt;The Evidence:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;!---
Chat title: The Power of Gentle Touch for Newborn Pain Relief

Zheln: summarize the below in bullet points

Claude 2 AI: Here are the key bullet points summarizing the article:

- Cochrane study analyzed data from 74 neonatal ICU patients across 4 randomized trials to see if facilitated tucking (gently bending a baby's arms and legs) reduces pain in neonates on mechanical ventilation undergoing endotracheal suctioning

- Moderate certainty that facilitated tucking reduces pain by 14-40% on the Premature Infant Pain Profile scale used, a change likely noticeable to doctors and caregivers 

- Wanted to assess other non-pharmaceutical treatments like rocking, skin-to-skin contact, or breastfeeding but only gentle touch techniques studied for this procedure

- Also wanted to look at outcomes like mortality, nausea/vomiting, hemorrhage but limited analysis to just pain scores

- Uncomfortable truth that medical procedures cause pain for newborns; early-life pain theorized to impact brain development with potentially devastating consequences  

- New evidence shows the difference gentle human touch can make in reducing procedural pain
---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cochrane.org/CD013353/NEONATAL_medicine-free-management-neonates-pain-during-endotracheal-suctioning&quot;&gt;Cochrane study&lt;/a&gt; analyzed data from 148 neonatal ICU patients across 4 randomized trials to see if facilitated tucking (gently bending a baby’s arms and legs) reduces pain in neonates on mechanical ventilation undergoing endotracheal suctioning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The scientists &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.cd013353.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Pirlotte S, Beeckman K, Ooms I, Cools F. Non-pharmacological interventions for the prevention of pain during endotracheal suctioning in ventilated neonates. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2024 Jan 18;1(1):CD013353. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD013353.pub2. PMID: 38235838; PMCID: PMC10795104.&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; moderate-certainty evidence that facilitated tucking reduces pain by 2.0 to 3.6 points on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s40138-016-0089-y&quot; title=&quot;Witt N, Coynor S, Edwards C, Bradshaw H. A Guide to Pain Assessment and Management in the Neonate. Curr Emerg Hosp Med Rep. 2016;4:1-10. doi: 10.1007/s40138-016-0089-y. Epub 2016 Mar 12. PMID: 27073748; PMCID: PMC4819510.&quot;&gt;Premature Infant Pain Profile&lt;/a&gt; scale used. Based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/pch/9.suppl_a.44aa&quot; title=&quot;Shah V, Ipp M, Sam J, Einarson T, Taddio A. Eliciting the minimal clinically important difference in the pain response from parents of newborn infants and nurses. Paediatrics &amp;amp; Child Health. 2004 May 1;9(suppl_a):44A-44A. doi: 10.1093/pch/9.suppl_a.44aa.&quot;&gt;previous studies&lt;/a&gt;, a drop of about 1.5 points is likely to be noticeable to some parents, and of 2.3 points to clinicians.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The researchers wanted to assess other non-pharmaceutical treatments like rocking, skin-to-skin contact, or breastfeeding, but only gentle touch techniques were well-studied for this procedure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They also wanted to look at outcomes like mortality, nausea/vomiting, and hemorrhage, but data unavailability forced the researchers to limit analyses to just pain scores.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This new evidence comes as hopeful news against the uncomfortable truth that medical procedures &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/archpedi.157.11.1058&quot; title=&quot;Simons SH, van Dijk M, Anand KS, Roofthooft D, van Lingen RA, Tibboel D. Do we still hurt newborn babies? A prospective study of procedural pain and analgesia in neonates. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2003 Nov;157(11):1058-64. doi: 10.1001/archpedi.157.11.1058. PMID: 14609893.&quot;&gt;cause newborns pain&lt;/a&gt;, with early-life pain &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41390-019-0744-6&quot; title=&quot;McPherson C, Miller SP, El-Dib M, Massaro AN, Inder TE. The influence of pain, agitation, and their management on the immature brain. Pediatr Res. 2020 Aug;88(2):168-175. doi: 10.1038/s41390-019-0744-6. Epub 2020 Jan 2. PMID: 31896130; PMCID: PMC7223850.&quot;&gt;theorized&lt;/a&gt; to impact brain development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-research&quot;&gt;The Research:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-a721f340-20b7-4386-90f9-0d3165023341?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to contract Zheln’s services or simply reach out, do &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. We can do anything that touches the realm of health research: from running a hardcore meta-analysis from scratch to publication, through holding an educational tutorial session for health professionals or the public, through speaking at an event or writing for your newspaper. The only thing we don’t provide is medical advice; but, we do provide medical evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post was created by a team of researchers and journalists with the help of multiple generative AI tools. Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;video bibliography&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2024-02-02-1.md&quot;&gt;Full changelog&lt;/a&gt; of this page is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The original Zheln whitepaper is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. The Power of Human Touch. Zheln. 2024 Feb  2;3(1):t9e4. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2024/02/02/1/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/25/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/02/16/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2024/02/02/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2024/02/02/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Seat-Belt Promotion Works</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;seatbelt-promotion-works-but-how-well&quot;&gt;Seatbelt promotion works. But how well?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;60-of-drivers-still-dont-use-seat-belts-and-even-more-passengers&quot;&gt;60% of drivers still don’t use seat belts (and even more passengers).&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2024-01-25-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;World country map of seat-belt law status, 2022. Source: Figure 15 from Global status report on road safety 2023. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2023. Licence: CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: As of January 2024, the map is no longer accurate because, for example, in Mexico, a law was enacted in 2022 that made seat belts &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reporteindigo.com/reporte/ley-de-movilidad-todos-los-pasajeros-deben-usar-el-cinturon-de-seguridad-en-todo-el-pais/&quot;&gt;obligatory for all passengers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-facts&quot;&gt;The Facts:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;!---
Chat title: Seat Belt Interventions: A Systematic Review of Education, Incentives, and Engineering Approaches

Zheln: Summarize the methods and findings of this study. Always preserve confidence intervals and certainty of evidence ratings. If there is a Summary of Findings table, focus your findings summary on it. Write in coherent text, not bullet points.

Claude 2 AI: This Cochrane systematic review analyzed 15 randomized controlled trials with 12,081 participants that evaluated education, engineering, and incentive-based interventions to promote seat belt use. The studies were conducted primarily in the US and recruited participants from various sites like worksites, schools, emergency departments etc.

The key findings were:

- Behavioral education interventions (e.g. motivational interviews, behavioral counseling) may improve seat belt use in adolescents and adults (low certainty evidence). A health risk appraisal intervention also likely improves seat belt use short-term (moderate certainty evidence).
- Engineering interventions like in-vehicle monitoring systems with alerts/feedback may promote seat belt use but the evidence is from only 2 small trials (low certainty evidence).
- None of the trials reported on crash-related injuries or deaths.

The authors conclude that while there is some evidence that education and engineering interventions may promote seat belt use, more high-quality research is needed particularly from low- and middle-income countries. Limitations include reliance on self-reported seat belt use data in most trials and small sample sizes testing engineering interventions. More research on incentives and other intervention types is also needed.
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of the usefulness of seat belts for the prevention of deaths and serious injuries in car accidents seems to be indisputable among public health officials. For example, the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/transportationsafety/seatbelts/facts.html&quot;&gt;advocate&lt;/a&gt; the use of seat belts, claiming that they “reduce serious crash-related injuries and deaths by about half” and reportedly “saved almost 15,000 lives in 2017,” based on U.S. data. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240086517&quot;&gt;Global status report on road safety 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by the reputable World Health Organization (WHO) warns, “Failure to use seat-belts is a major risk factor for road traffic deaths and injuries among vehicle occupants,” and commends seat-belt mandates, shown in the image above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look up some of the evidence cited, seat belts &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-018-6280-1&quot; title=&quot;Fouda Mbarga N, Abubakari AR, Aminde LN, Morgan AR. Seatbelt use and risk of major injuries sustained by vehicle occupants during motor-vehicle crashes: a systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies. BMC Public Health. 2018 Dec 29;18(1):1413. doi: 10.1186/s12889-018-6280-1. PMID: 30594164; PMCID: PMC6310927.&quot;&gt;were tentatively found&lt;/a&gt; to reduce the risk of overall injuries, but a subgroup analysis by the location of the critical injury gave inconclusive results, meaning that some types of injuries may actually be unprevented by seat belts, such as head, neck, or chest trauma. This does not necessarily mean seat belts don’t work. In fact, seat belts are associated with an &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajem.2023.11.058&quot; title=&quot;Pourmand A, Terrebonne E, Shapovalov V, Kartiko S, AlRemeithi R, Tran QK. Prevalence of intra-abdominal injury among patients with seatbelt signs, a systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Emerg Med. 2024 Feb;76:199-206. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2023.11.058. Epub 2023 Dec 3. PMID: 38086186.&quot;&gt;abdominal injury of their own&lt;/a&gt;, even though the risk of overall abdominal injuries decreases, as the aforementioned subgroup analysis suggests. The physics of seat belts in simulated car crashes &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-youtube&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9_Af8w2SAT4&quot;&gt;make it visual&lt;/a&gt; how they work: by restraining the user, they won’t let them move forward after the car has crashed against a barrier, which hopefully saves lives. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/1749-7922-6-18&quot; title=&quot;Abbas AK, Hefny AF, Abu-Zidan FM. Seatbelts and road traffic collision injuries. World J Emerg Surg. 2011 May 28;6(1):18. doi: 10.1186/1749-7922-6-18. PMID: 21619677; PMCID: PMC3121590.&quot;&gt;2011 analysis&lt;/a&gt; based on WHO’s data from 46 high-income countries showed that seat-belt compliance was strongly associated with road traffic death rates. There is room for speculation about causality here, however, as these are high-level data that do not preclude the existence of a third variable that improves both seat-belt compliance and motor vehicle accident statistics, thus remaining masked in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD011218.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Lourens A, Sinclair M, Willems B, Young T. Education, incentive, and engineering-based interventions to promote the use of seat belts. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2024 Jan 10;1(1):CD011218. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD011218.pub2. PMID: 38197528; PMCID: PMC10777455.&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt; by Cochrane, the world’s leader in synthesizing medical evidence, went unnoticed in the news media (&lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;see our research&lt;/a&gt;). This analysis looked at the effectiveness of activities promoting the use of seat belts. The activities studied included various education formats offered in sites such as workplaces, schools, or health care organizations, and a couple of trials investigated in-vehicle data monitoring and alert systems, with the majority of data collection conducted in the US. Cochrane has already published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cochrane.org/CD011218/INJ_interventions-encourage-use-seat-belts&quot;&gt;useful summary&lt;/a&gt; of this study for the general public, which concluded that they “found some evidence to suggest education-based (behavioural and health risk appraisal (HRA)) and engineering-based interventions may promote seat-belt use in early and late adolescents and adults; however, we are not confident in the current evidence.” Zheln &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;has reviewed&lt;/a&gt; their entire scientific report and confirms that this statement is accurate. To elaborate a bit on what exactly Cochrane did in this study, they looked at 15 randomized trials encompassing over 12,000 participants but were unable to combine these data due to their very mixed nature, so they ended up looking at each trial separately. It’s also of note that all 15 trials had a high risk of inflated findings, but that was more of a limitation of the study setting than a failure on the researchers’ part. Importantly, none of the trials reported on crash-related injuries or deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best takeaway from this complex picture is probably that our understanding of how the seat belt, or rather, seat-belt promotion works in practice is still quite vague. A previous study found &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/15389588.2021.1921168&quot; title=&quot;Akbari M, Lankarani KB, Tabrizi R, Heydari ST, Vali M, Motevalian SA, Sullman MJM. The effectiveness of mass media campaigns in increasing the use of seat belts: A systematic review. Traffic Inj Prev. 2021;22(7):495-500. doi: 10.1080/15389588.2021.1921168. Epub 2021 Aug 6. PMID: 34355980.&quot;&gt;modest but positive&lt;/a&gt; evidence of the effectiveness of mass media campaigns in increasing the use of seat belts. A US-based analysis &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0001-4575(03)00038-1&quot; title=&quot;Shults RA, Elder RW, Sleet DA, Thompson RS, Nichols JL. Primary enforcement seat belt laws are effective even in the face of rising belt use rates. Accid Anal Prev. 2004 May;36(3):491-3. doi: 10.1016/S0001-4575(03)00038-1. PMID: 15003594.&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; a median increase of 33 percentage points in observed seat-belt use after the enactment of seat-belt enforcement laws. With all these measures in place, seat-belt use is still far from universal: its pooled global rate, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s42506-023-00139-3&quot; title=&quot;Kargar S, Ansari-Moghaddam A, Ansari H. The prevalence of seat belt use among drivers and passengers: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Egypt Public Health Assoc. 2023 Aug 2;98(1):14. doi: 10.1186/s42506-023-00139-3. PMID: 37528241; PMCID: PMC10393920.&quot;&gt;as of 2020&lt;/a&gt;, was at about 40% for drivers, 35% for front-seat passengers, and 10–15% for rear-seat passengers. We can also clearly see how the evidence in which the effectiveness claims are grounded is predominantly US-based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evidence&quot;&gt;The Evidence:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;!---
Chat title: Seat Belt Use Rates and Evidence in Different Vehicle Seats

Zheln: summarize the above in bullet points

Claude 2 AI:  Here are the key points from the document summarized in bullet points:

- Public health organizations like the CDC and WHO advocate for seat belt use, claiming they reduce crash-related injuries and deaths by about half and saved 15,000 lives in the US in 2017.

- Evidence on seat belt effectiveness is inconclusive for some types of injuries - they may prevent overall injuries but not certain ones like head, neck or chest trauma. 

- Physics shows how seat belts restrain occupants and prevent them from moving forward in a crash.

- Analysis of WHO data associates seat belt compliance with lower traffic death rates across 46 high-income countries, but causality is speculative.  

- A recent Cochrane review found some evidence that education and in-vehicle alerts may promote seat belt use in adolescents and adults, but the evidence is not very confident.

- The Cochrane review looked at 15 small randomized trials but couldn't combine the data due to heterogeneity. None of the trials measured crash-related outcomes.

- Understanding the real-world effectiveness of seat belt promotion is still quite vague. Other analyses find positive impacts of media campaigns and laws on seat belt use.

- Despite promotion efforts, seat belt use rates remain low globally - around 40% for drivers, 35% for front passengers and 10-15% for rear passengers.

- Most evidence on seat belt effectiveness is from the US context.
---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public health organizations like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/transportationsafety/seatbelts/facts.html&quot;&gt;CDC&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240086517&quot;&gt;WHO&lt;/a&gt; advocate for seat-belt use, claiming they reduce crash-related injuries and deaths by about half and save thousands of lives yearly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence on seat-belt effectiveness is &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-018-6280-1&quot; title=&quot;Fouda Mbarga N, Abubakari AR, Aminde LN, Morgan AR. Seatbelt use and risk of major injuries sustained by vehicle occupants during motor-vehicle crashes: a systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies. BMC Public Health. 2018 Dec 29;18(1):1413. doi: 10.1186/s12889-018-6280-1. PMID: 30594164; PMCID: PMC6310927.&quot;&gt;inconclusive&lt;/a&gt; for some types of injuries – they may prevent overall injuries but not certain ones like head, neck, or chest trauma.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Car crash simulations &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9_Af8w2SAT4&quot;&gt;show&lt;/a&gt; how seat belts restrain occupants and prevent them from moving forward during an accident.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analysis of WHO data &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/1749-7922-6-18&quot; title=&quot;Abbas AK, Hefny AF, Abu-Zidan FM. Seatbelts and road traffic collision injuries. World J Emerg Surg. 2011 May 28;6(1):18. doi: 10.1186/1749-7922-6-18. PMID: 21619677; PMCID: PMC3121590.&quot;&gt;associates&lt;/a&gt; seat-belt compliance with lower road death rates across 46 high-income countries, but causality is speculative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cochrane.org/CD011218/INJ_interventions-encourage-use-seat-belts&quot;&gt;recent Cochrane review&lt;/a&gt; found some evidence that education and in-vehicle alerts may promote seat-belt use in adolescents and adults, but the evidence is not very certain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD011218.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Lourens A, Sinclair M, Willems B, Young T. Education, incentive, and engineering-based interventions to promote the use of seat belts. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2024 Jan 10;1(1):CD011218. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD011218.pub2. PMID: 38197528; PMCID: PMC10777455.&quot;&gt;Cochrane review&lt;/a&gt; looked at over 12,000 across 15 randomized trials but couldn’t combine the data due to heterogeneity. None of the trials measured crash-related outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other analyses found positive impacts of &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/15389588.2021.1921168&quot; title=&quot;Akbari M, Lankarani KB, Tabrizi R, Heydari ST, Vali M, Motevalian SA, Sullman MJM. The effectiveness of mass media campaigns in increasing the use of seat belts: A systematic review. Traffic Inj Prev. 2021;22(7):495-500. doi: 10.1080/15389588.2021.1921168. Epub 2021 Aug 6. PMID: 34355980.&quot;&gt;media campaigns&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0001-4575(03)00038-1&quot; title=&quot;Shults RA, Elder RW, Sleet DA, Thompson RS, Nichols JL. Primary enforcement seat belt laws are effective even in the face of rising belt use rates. Accid Anal Prev. 2004 May;36(3):491-3. doi: 10.1016/S0001-4575(03)00038-1. PMID: 15003594.&quot;&gt;laws&lt;/a&gt; on seat-belt use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Despite promotion efforts, seat-belt use rates &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s42506-023-00139-3&quot; title=&quot;Kargar S, Ansari-Moghaddam A, Ansari H. The prevalence of seat belt use among drivers and passengers: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Egypt Public Health Assoc. 2023 Aug 2;98(1):14. doi: 10.1186/s42506-023-00139-3. PMID: 37528241; PMCID: PMC10393920.&quot;&gt;remain low globally&lt;/a&gt; – around 40% for drivers, 35% for front passengers, and 10–15% for rear passengers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most evidence on seat-belt effectiveness comes from the U.S. context.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In summary, our understanding of the real-world effectiveness of seat-belt promotion is still quite vague.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-research&quot;&gt;The Research:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-ac9f25e9-b221-4125-94e3-cf1259caeb2b?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to contract Zheln’s services or simply reach out, do &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. We can do anything that touches the realm of health research: from running a hardcore meta-analysis from scratch to publication, through holding an educational tutorial session for health professionals or the public, through speaking at an event or writing for your newspaper. The only thing we don’t provide is medical advice; but, we do provide medical evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post was created by a team of researchers and journalists with the help of multiple generative AI tools. Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;video bibliography&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2024-01-25-1.md&quot;&gt;Full changelog&lt;/a&gt; of this page is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The original Zheln whitepaper is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. How Seat-Belt Promotion Works. Zheln. 2024 Jan 25;2(1):t8e3. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/25/1/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/18/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/02/02/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/25/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/25/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Story of Flu Trials</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;tamiflu-not-shown-to-prevent-severe-flu&quot;&gt;Tamiflu not shown to prevent severe flu.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consumer-advice-is-not-clear-on-this-so-we-reiterate&quot;&gt;Consumer advice is not clear on this, so we reiterate.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2024-01-18-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Feature image - The Story of Flu Trials. Image credit: Tony Hisgett, June 19, 2009. License: CC BY 2.0.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-facts&quot;&gt;The Facts:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tamiflu, an anti-flu medication, reduces the duration of illness by about half a day on average and prevents 2­–4% of cases of symptomatic flu, but it does not prevent positive lab tests if the person has no symptoms, and it also increases the rate of nausea, vomiting, and headache. This is the evidence from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD008965.pub4&quot; title=&quot;Jefferson T, Jones MA, Doshi P, Del Mar CB, Hama R, Thompson MJ, Spencer EA, Onakpoya I, Mahtani KR, Nunan D, Howick J, Heneghan CJ. Neuraminidase inhibitors for preventing and treating influenza in adults and children. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Apr 10;2014(4):CD008965. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008965.pub4. PMID: 24718923; PMCID: PMC6464969.&quot;&gt;major 2014 study&lt;/a&gt;, whose results are mirrored pretty accurately in two of Google’s top hits for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=tamiflu&quot;&gt;Tamiflu&lt;/a&gt;, consumer webpages by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/tamiflu-consumer-questions-and-answers&quot;&gt;U.S. Food &amp;amp; Drug Administration&lt;/a&gt; (FDA) and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/human/EPAR/tamiflu&quot;&gt;European Medicines Agency&lt;/a&gt; (EMA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tamiflu has not been shown to reduce deaths or hospitalizations. The agencies are not trying to make it look like it did, but they are not particularly vocal about this either. True: absence of evidence is not evidence of absence; but, when multiple well conducted trials failed to prove the effect, it might be worth highlighting these findings. Otherwise, it is just logical to assume that if the drug is &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-youtube&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5LSP02MkNOU&quot;&gt;active against viruses&lt;/a&gt;, then it should reduce the risk of severe illness. At short notice, Zheln did not find much evidence people actually assume that, but at least one of the top Google results does seem to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parents.com/health/cold-flu/flu/tamiflu-and-kids-everything-parents-need-to-know/&quot;&gt;follow this logic&lt;/a&gt;; “Early treatment with Tamiflu can lead to milder illness, which lessens the number of hospitalizations and deaths associated with the flu,” they write. However, other top Google hits are pretty circumspect in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drugs.com/tips/tamiflu-patient-tips&quot;&gt;giving account&lt;/a&gt; of Tamiflu’s effects. One doctor author &lt;a href=&quot;https://health.mountsinai.org/blog/is-it-worth-it-to-take-tamiflu/&quot;&gt;suggested&lt;/a&gt; that “expectations for Tamiflu are often very high and, frankly, overhyped.” A 2022 news story &lt;a href=&quot;https://montreal.ctvnews.ca/quebec-to-offer-free-antiviral-flu-drug-in-pharmacies-1.6192420&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that health authorities of one of the regions of Canada worked to offer Tamiflu for free, with a high official saying, “It’s quite effective to prevent complications, hospitalizations.” All in all, it looks like it is worth revisiting the disheartening evidence related to Tamiflu, particularly because a newer study was &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0699&quot; title=&quot;Hanula R, Bortolussi-Courval É, Mendel A, Ward BJ, Lee TC, McDonald EG. Evaluation of Oseltamivir Used to Prevent Hospitalization in Outpatients With Influenza: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. JAMA Intern Med. 2024 Jan 1;184(1):18-27. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0699. Erratum in: JAMA Intern Med. 2023 Nov 20;: PMID: 37306992; PMCID: PMC10262060.&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; in 2023, focusing specifically on the rate of hospital treatment on Tamiflu versus placebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zheln is not the first to cover that recent study: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jwatch.org/na56236/2023/07/06/oseltamivir-doesnt-prevent-hospitalizations-outpatients&quot;&gt;New England Journal of Medicine Journal Watch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infectiousdiseaseadvisor.com/home/topics/respiratory/influenza/does-oseltamivir-prevent-all-cause-hospitalization-in-outpatients-with-influenza/&quot;&gt;InfectiousDisease Advisor&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medicalxpress.com/news/2023-06-oseltamivir-linked-flu-hospitalization.html&quot;&gt;MedicalXpress&lt;/a&gt; highlighted the findings of the study, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medpagetoday.com/infectiousdisease/uritheflu/104963&quot;&gt;MedPage Today&lt;/a&gt; also did a great job interviewing one of the study authors. If you read all of these publications, there is not much Zheln can add, honestly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important takeaway would be that when 3,000 mostly White outpatients in their 40s, with flu but relatively healthy otherwise, were treated with Tamiflu across 15 randomized trials, about the same 25 people eventually required hospital treatment as in the similar 3,000 patient group that took placebo and/or standard therapy. Additionally, the rate of nausea or vomiting was at least 13% higher and at most 2.6 times as high on Tamiflu. The quality of the trials was high enough for the researchers to be moderately certain of these findings, making the evidence somewhat less likely to change with future trials being added to the big picture. Zheln’s fifty cents would be that the piece of information enclosed in this paragraph essentially is the evidence – just some numbers with a pinch of scientific scrutiny over it. An important feature of evidence, the reader is free to interpret it the way they see fit. It’s also good to keep in mind that this stuff is as scientific as iPhones, X-rays, or antibiotics, just less visible and tangible (think astronomy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evidence&quot;&gt;The Evidence:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;!---
Zheln: summarize the below in bullet points:

Claude 2 AI:  Here are the key points summarized in bullet points:

- A major 2014 study found that Tamiflu reduces flu illness duration by about half a day on average and prevents some flu cases from happening. This aligns with info from the FDA and European Medicines Agency.

- Tamiflu has not been shown to reduce deaths or hospitalizations from the flu.

- A 2023 study of over 6,100 people with the flu found no difference in hospitalizations between those given Tamiflu vs those given placebo or standard therapy.

- The study participants were relatively healthy - in their 40s on average, mostly White or Asian, with few chronic illnesses. 

- If Tamiflu worked as well as advertised, the number of hospitalizations should have dropped at least twofold, from 25 to 12 or less. But the actual number was statistically no different.

- The evidence on Tamiflu is just some numbers with scientific scrutiny. Science is like a board game - you learn some lore and you can interpret data.

- People with a disease are important decision makers, not just health professionals. The health care system should serve their best interests.
---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD008965.pub4&quot; title=&quot;Jefferson T, Jones MA, Doshi P, Del Mar CB, Hama R, Thompson MJ, Spencer EA, Onakpoya I, Mahtani KR, Nunan D, Howick J, Heneghan CJ. Neuraminidase inhibitors for preventing and treating influenza in adults and children. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Apr 10;2014(4):CD008965. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008965.pub4. PMID: 24718923; PMCID: PMC6464969.&quot;&gt;2014 Cochrane systematic review&lt;/a&gt; found that Tamiflu (oseltamivir) reduces flu illness duration by 8–25 hours on average and prevents 2 cases in every 52­–110 cases of symptomatic influenza from happening, but not cases without symptoms. The risk of headache, nausea, and vomiting was higher on treatment. This aligns with info from some of Google’s top hits on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=tamiflu&quot;&gt;Tamiflu&lt;/a&gt;, such as those from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/tamiflu-consumer-questions-and-answers&quot;&gt;FDA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/human/EPAR/tamiflu&quot;&gt;European Medicines Agency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the same study, oseltamivir has not been shown to reduce deaths or hospitalizations from flu, pooling the data from 7 randomized trials and 4,400 patients, a fact not prominent in the agencies’ statements. However, a brief overview of Google’s top hits revealed that the assumption that Tamiflu prevents serious flu, arising from the general interpretation of its antiviral properties, is not uncommon among the public.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0699&quot; title=&quot;Hanula R, Bortolussi-Courval É, Mendel A, Ward BJ, Lee TC, McDonald EG. Evaluation of Oseltamivir Used to Prevent Hospitalization in Outpatients With Influenza: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. JAMA Intern Med. 2024 Jan 1;184(1):18-27. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0699. Erratum in: JAMA Intern Med. 2023 Nov 20;: PMID: 37306992; PMCID: PMC10262060.&quot;&gt;2023 systematic review&lt;/a&gt; included 15 randomized trials and over 6,100 patients with flu and found no difference in hospitalizations between those given Tamiflu versus those given placebo and/or standard therapy. Additionally, the rate of vomiting was 28% to 163% higher on Tamiflu, and the rate of nausea was 13% to 82% higher. The study participants were mostly White or Asian, in their 40s on average, and with few chronic illnesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The quality of the trials was high enough for the researchers to claim moderate certainty of the evidence, making it somewhat less likely to change when future trials are added to the big picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-research&quot;&gt;The Research:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-6c6bfa5d-2be7-44d6-8bea-2ab44ce968ab?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to contract Zheln’s services or simply reach out, do &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. We can do anything that touches the realm of health research: from running a hardcore meta-analysis from scratch to publication, through holding an educational tutorial session for health professionals or the public, through speaking at an event or writing for your newspaper. The only thing we don’t provide is medical advice; but, we do provide medical evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post was created by a team of researchers and journalists with the help of multiple generative AI tools. Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;video bibliography&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2024-01-18-1.md&quot;&gt;Full changelog&lt;/a&gt; of this page is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The original Zheln whitepaper is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. The Story of Flu Trials. Zheln. 2024 Jan 18;1(1):t7e4. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/18/1/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/11/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/25/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/18/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/18/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Picking Therapies for Liver Cancer</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-doctors-know-which-cancer-treatment-is-better&quot;&gt;How can doctors know which cancer treatment is better?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-reading-this-post-you-will-be-able-to-understand-this-image&quot;&gt;After reading this post, you will be able to understand this image:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2024-01-11-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Feature image - Picking Therapies for Liver Cancer. Image source, distributed under CC BY 4.0: Wade R et al. Ablative and non-surgical therapies for early and very early hepatocellular carcinoma: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. NIHR Journals Library. doi: 10.3310/GK5221&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-facts&quot;&gt;The Facts:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;!---
Zheln: Summarize this in engaging plain language:

- A 200-page research report was [published][wade_ablative_2023] in December 2023 that explored evidence on novel treatments of early-stage liver cancer, otherwise known as hepatocellular carcinoma. With respect to this particular cancer, early-stage means the size of the neoplasm less than 3 cm and no distant tumor growth. - Using advanced statistical techniques, invented just 5 to 20 years ago, the researchers compared multiple treatments, including high-energy destruction, irradiation, chemo, and surgery. Additionally, they were able to account for the quality of scientific data by forecasting the impact that it may have on the numbers. - The scientists ranked treatment techniques by their efficacy and calculated the amount of numerical change needed to “overthrow” the top-performing procedure in the “league table.” Two groups of metrics were used to assess efficacy: patient survival (overall and progression-free) and tumor recurrence (overall and local). - This evidence suggested unusual conclusions that contradict clinical judgement or tumor biology; the most radical treatment, liver surgery, commonly thought to be the most effective treatment due to the full removal of the neoplasm, performed worse than more “dirty” techniques such as high-energy destruction (ablation), sometimes combined with irradiation or chemo. - This evidence illustrates the state-of-the-art scientific techniques employed for picking the best treatment from a range of possible options.

Claude: Here is a 147-word plain language summary of the key points from the research report:

A major medical study published last month overturned common assumptions about the best way to treat early-stage liver cancer. Researchers compared multiple treatments, including surgery, irradiation, chemotherapy, and a newer technique called high-energy destruction or ablation. Using cutting-edge statistical methods, they ranked treatments based on patient survival rates and cancer recurrence levels. 

Surprisingly, the study found that completely removing tumors through surgery - long seen as the gold standard - was less effective than less radical options like ablation, sometimes combined with irradiation or chemo. The full surgical removal of tumors is commonly thought to be the most successful approach.  

However, the advanced number-crunching techniques used in this study accounted for the quality of data from different treatments and still found ablation outperformed surgery. This shows how the latest scientific methods can challenge clinical assumptions and help identify better options among various possible treatments. The study demonstrates a state-of-the-art approach for determining optimal medical therapies.
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major medical study &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3310/GK5221&quot; title=&quot;Wade R, South E, Anwer S, Sharif-Hurst S, Harden M, Fulbright H, Hodgson R, Dias S, Simmonds M, Rowe I, Thornton P, Eastwood A. Ablative and non-surgical therapies for early and very early hepatocellular carcinoma: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Health Technol Assess. 2023 Dec;27(29):1-172. doi: 10.3310/GK5221. PMID: 38149643.&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; in December 2023 challenged a common assumption about the best way to treat cancer. Researchers compared multiple treatments of early-stage liver cancer, including surgery, irradiation, chemotherapy, and a newer technique called high-energy destruction or ablation. Using cutting-edge statistical methods, they ranked treatments based on patient survival rates and cancer recurrence levels, accounting for statistical variation and study quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the study found that completely removing tumors through surgery – long seen by cancer specialists as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/liver-cancer/treating/surgery.html&quot;&gt;“gold standard”&lt;/a&gt; – is no better than less radical options, like ablation, while still leading to more adverse events, including postoperative complications, major complications, and serious pain requiring painkillers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ablation is the destruction of body tissues using high energies, like heat, microwaves, or laser. It’s often paired with chemotherapy or radiation treatments. The figure above is usually called a “forest plot,” but we’ll use a more practical metaphor: Imagine that each black horizontal line in the image is a track runner, representing a cancer treatment, and the vertical dashed line is the finish line. The blue dot is the runner’s head (the estimated effect from the trials; in this case, overall survival), and the line is the span of the runner’s step (the probability range of the effect estimate, a so-called credibility interval). Our runners are moving from the right to the left, striving to cross the finish line, as in this running track close-up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2024-01-11-1_running_track_close-up.png&quot; alt=&quot;Running track close-up. Image source: public domain.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The positive effect is expressed as a negative number because it means fewer bad events (e.g., deaths), versus “standard therapy” (e.g., radiofrequency ablation). The runner who is the first to cross the finish line completely (with both the head and the feet) becomes the winner. This study attempts to challenge the winning treatment under various statistical conditions, trying to answer the question: Are we sure it is truly better than standard therapy, not incidentally? Maybe the trials generated this spuriously outstanding performance because they were biased, just like a runner suspected of doping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As investigators, we artificially increase and decrease trial results to see how much change the calculations can tolerate before the best-case scenario switches to some other treatment option. Imagine that our runners are riding slugs, represented by light-blue bands, which show the extended probability range that takes trial quality into account (so-called invariant intervals). The slug needs to drag their entire slimey body beyond the finish line before the rider can complete the race. Can you now see which treatment is winning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: the winner is the 6th slug from the top, representing radiofrequency ablation combined with the implantation of radioactive iodine-125 into the tumor. The head, the feet, and the slug are all across the finish line, so we can be pretty certain of the trial data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, look at the 4th band, with the gray bar? That rider has real promise but got ahead of their own slug, which is against the rules, and was disqualified. This 4th line is microwave ablation, and it has a chance of competing with the top-choice procedure, radiofrequency ablation plus radioactive substance, but only if more high-quality trials show its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, the traditional hardcore surgery (liver resection) is the 3rd line from the top – can you now tell how well it performed versus radiofrequency ablation? This example shows how the latest scientific methods can challenge clinical assumptions and help pick better options among various possible treatments based on the bulk evidence from human trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evidence&quot;&gt;The Evidence:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An over-200-page research report was &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3310/GK5221&quot; title=&quot;Wade R, South E, Anwer S, Sharif-Hurst S, Harden M, Fulbright H, Hodgson R, Dias S, Simmonds M, Rowe I, Thornton P, Eastwood A. Ablative and non-surgical therapies for early and very early hepatocellular carcinoma: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Health Technol Assess. 2023 Dec;27(29):1-172. doi: 10.3310/GK5221. PMID: 38149643.&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; in December 2023 that explored evidence on novel treatments of early-stage liver cancer, otherwise known as hepatocellular carcinoma. With respect to this particular cancer, early-stage means the size of the neoplasm less than 3 cm and no distant tumor growth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using advanced statistical techniques, developed over the last 25 years (called network meta-analysis), the researchers compared multiple treatments, including high-energy destruction (ablation, laser), irradiation, chemo, surgery (liver resection), ethanol and acid injections, and other dangerous stuff. Additionally, they were able to account for the quality of scientific data by forecasting the impact that it may have on the numbers (using a technique called threshold analysis).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The scientists ranked treatment procedures by their efficacy and calculated the amount of numerical change needed to “overthrow” the top-performing procedure in the “league table.” Two groups of metrics were used to assess efficacy: patient survival (overall and progression-free) and tumor recurrence (overall and local).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The evidence suggested unusual conclusions that contradict clinical judgment or common-sense tumor biology; the most radical treatment, liver surgery, commonly thought to be the most effective treatment due to the full removal of the neoplasm, performed no better than more “dirty” techniques such as radiofrequency ablation. This conclusion stood even when study quality and statistical variation were taken into account.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additionally, the implantation of radioactive iodine-125 (brachytherapy) boosted the effect of radiofrequency ablation, based on overall survival, and was forecasted to improve overall tumor recurrence rates in future trials. Microwave ablation is a promising competitor of radiofrequency ablation and could outperform it by overall survival and local disease recurrence in future trials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This evidence illustrates the state-of-the-art scientific techniques employed for picking the best treatment from a range of possible options, as well as selecting the most promising candidates for future studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-research&quot;&gt;The Research:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-104ab099-ad88-4f7e-87ec-c4421f156026?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to contract Zheln’s services or simply reach out, do &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. We can do anything that touches the realm of health research: from running a hardcore meta-analysis from scratch to publication, through holding an educational tutorial session for health professionals or the public, through speaking at an event or writing for your newspaper. The only thing we don’t provide is medical advice; but, we do provide medical evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post was created by a team of researchers and journalists with the help of multiple generative AI tools. Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;video bibliography&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2024-01-11-1.md&quot;&gt;Full changelog&lt;/a&gt; of this page is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The original Zheln whitepaper is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. Picking Therapies for Liver Cancer. Zheln. 2024 Jan 11;52(1):t6e1. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/11/1/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/04/2/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/18/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/11/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/11/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cranberries for Urinary Infections</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-evidence-cranberry-juice-is-helpful-for-urinary-infections-in-pregnancy-multiple-studies-find&quot;&gt;No evidence cranberry juice is helpful for urinary infections in pregnancy, multiple studies find.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-is-a-mild-preventative-effect-among-children-and-non-pregnant-women-with-recurrent-utis--but-those-findings-are-still-provisional&quot;&gt;There is a mild preventative effect among children and non-pregnant women with recurrent UTIs ­– but those findings are still provisional.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2024-01-04-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cranberry UTI Evidence Journey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-facts&quot;&gt;The Facts:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to folk wisdom, many top Google results, including the prestigious-sounding Medical News Today, and the now ubiquitous opinions of ChatGPT, there’s no good evidence that cranberry juice does anything to treat urinary tract infections. That’s the conclusion reached by a high-quality evidence review &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001322&quot; title=&quot;Jepson RG, Mihaljevic L, Craig JC. Cranberries for treating urinary tract infections. Cochrane Kidney and Transplant Group, editor. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews [Internet]. 1998 Oct 26 [cited 2023 Dec 23]; Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001322&quot;&gt;first published&lt;/a&gt; back in 1998 and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001322.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Jepson RG, Mihaljevic L, Craig JC. Cranberries for treating urinary tract infections. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023 Dec 14;12(12):CD001322. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001322.pub2. PMID: 38096261; PMCID: PMC10721117.&quot;&gt;last updated&lt;/a&gt; in December 2023. Neither the old nor the updated version found any trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, another review, focused on prevention, rather than treatment, did find tons of evidence. Back in 2012, it &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub5&quot; title=&quot;Jepson RG, Williams G, Craig JC. Cranberries for preventing urinary tract infections. Cochrane Kidney and Transplant Group, editor. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews [Internet]. 2012 Oct 17 [cited 2023 Dec 24];2014(6). Available from: http://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub5&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; no preventive effect despite the findings of 24 trials with over 4,400 participants. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub7&quot; title=&quot;Williams G, Stothart CI, Hahn D, Stephens JH, Craig JC, Hodson EM. Cranberries for preventing urinary tract infections. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023 Nov 10;11(11):CD001321. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub7. PMID: 37947276; PMCID: PMC10636779.&quot;&gt;updated version&lt;/a&gt; from November 2023 was able to detect a small reduction in urinary tract infection (UTI) rates after the data from another 26 trials were added – but, we probably shouldn’t get too excited just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When subgroup analyses were performed, reduced UTI rates were found among women with recurrent UTIs and among children but were not confirmed among elderly inpatients, patients with urinary leakage, and pregnant women. Given an &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; 16% of pregnant women suffer from UTIs (or 20 million people at any given time), this is a disappointing result. Interviews of women who had UTI in pregnancy &lt;a href=&quot;https://pesquisa.bvsalud.org/portal/resource/pt/bde-29996&quot; title=&quot;Alves de Almeida AP, de Souza de Jesus LM, Costa Maia Dias IC, de Fátima Fernandes MN, Santos Mourão IS, Nogueira Ferreira AG. Hospitalization of recurring urinary tract infection: perception of pregnant women. J Nurs UFPE/Revista de Enfermagem UFPE. 2016;10(Supl. 5):4233-4239. doi: 10.5205/1981-8963-v10i5a11168p4233-4239-2016.&quot;&gt;showed&lt;/a&gt; that this health condition is no minor concern to them; it aches, and the fear of serious harms to the baby is common. The need to take antibiotics &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.13044&quot; title=&quot;Ghouri F, Hollywood A, Ryan K. 'There is no choice apart from antibiotics…': Qualitative analysis of views on urinary infections in pregnancy and antimicrobial resistance. Health Expect. 2020 Jun;23(3):644-650. doi: 10.1111/hex.13044. Epub 2020 Feb 29. PMID: 32113189; PMCID: PMC7321732.&quot;&gt;worsens&lt;/a&gt; the fear and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-019-2451-z&quot; title=&quot;Ghouri F, Hollywood A, Ryan K. Urinary tract infections and antibiotic use in pregnancy - qualitative analysis of online forum content. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2019 Aug 13;19(1):289. doi: 10.1186/s12884-019-2451-z. PMID: 31409404; PMCID: PMC6693226.&quot;&gt;makes&lt;/a&gt; them consider other therapy options, such as cranberry pills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evidence&quot;&gt;The Evidence:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A reputable Cochrane meta-analysis &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001322&quot; title=&quot;Jepson RG, Mihaljevic L, Craig JC. Cranberries for treating urinary tract infections. Cochrane Kidney and Transplant Group, editor. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews [Internet]. 1998 Oct 26 [cited 2023 Dec 23]; Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001322&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; in 1998 and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001322.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Jepson RG, Mihaljevic L, Craig JC. Cranberries for treating urinary tract infections. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023 Dec 14;12(12):CD001322. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001322.pub2. PMID: 38096261; PMCID: PMC10721117.&quot;&gt;updated&lt;/a&gt; in December 2023 found no trials of cranberry products being used for treating UTIs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another Cochrane meta-analysis, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub7&quot; title=&quot;Williams G, Stothart CI, Hahn D, Stephens JH, Craig JC, Hodson EM. Cranberries for preventing urinary tract infections. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023 Nov 10;11(11):CD001321. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub7. PMID: 37947276; PMCID: PMC10636779.&quot;&gt;updated&lt;/a&gt; in November 2023, focused on prevention and found a small reduction in UTI rates in those who consumed cranberry juice or cranberry products compared to those who took placebo, water, or no specific prescription.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The certainty of evidence of the preventive effect is moderate, meaning that the estimate of effect might change in the future when new trials are published. This already happened with the 2023 update when it managed to detect the preventive effect of cranberry products, after the original 2012 review, encompassing half as many trials, failed to detect it with moderate certainty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The evidence is controversial to date for elderly inpatients, patients with urinary leakage, and pregnant women, as there were fewer trials that studied these subgroups.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The lack of preventive effectiveness among pregnant women is important as they suffer from UTIs at a high rate and with additional severity, as &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; of women’s lived experience detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;top-hits-on-google-are-ignorant-of-important-evidence&quot;&gt;Top hits on Google are ignorant of important evidence.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running a Google search for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=cranberry+utis&quot;&gt;cranberry + UTIs&lt;/a&gt; produces top results, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medical News Today, in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/306498&quot;&gt;2016 article&lt;/a&gt;, failed to account for the reputable Cochrane review, which, at that time, showed no evidence of preventive effectiveness of cranberry products. By contrast, the article cherry-picked just &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajog.2015.04.003&quot;&gt;one trial&lt;/a&gt; (out of at least 24 known at the time) and suggested that cranberry capsules “reduce the prevalence of UTI.” This is despite their claims of having “strict sourcing guidelines.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HealthEssentials Cleveland Clinic also failed to acknowledge the Cochrane review in their post on cranberries, &lt;a href=&quot;https://health.clevelandclinic.org/can-cranberry-juice-stop-uti&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; in 2020, claiming, “One 2013 analysis of 13 different trials concluded that cranberry juice and tablets did reduce the occurrence of UTIs compared to placebo in women with recurrent UTIs. But another review found that they didn’t.” Neither reference led to the major Cochrane review. The outlet ended up turning to a doctor who suggested, “Cranberry won’t hurt, but it may help,” ignoring scientific evidence whatsoever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chatgpt-is-unaware-of-the-evidence&quot;&gt;ChatGPT is unaware of the evidence.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT, asked if cranberries were “effective against urinary tract infections,” told us they are “believed” to have an active compound, proanthocyanidins, but “the evidence regarding the effectiveness of cranberries in preventing or treating UTIs is mixed.” Without actually showing the evidence and discussing its nuance, this is nothing more than a bland statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;when-science-is-done-right&quot;&gt;When science is done right…&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the research for this article, two systematic reviews were encountered, published in the same year, conducted by different teams (one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub7&quot; title=&quot;Williams G, Stothart CI, Hahn D, Stephens JH, Craig JC, Hodson EM. Cranberries for preventing urinary tract infections. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023 Nov 10;11(11):CD001321. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001321.pub7. PMID: 37947276; PMCID: PMC10636779.&quot;&gt;Australia&lt;/a&gt; and the other from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.46738&quot; title=&quot;Bolgarina Z, Gonzalez-Gonzalez LF, Rodroiguez GV, Camacho A. Cranberry Supplements for Urinary Tract Infection Prophylaxis in Pregnant Women: A Systematic Review of Clinical Trials and Observational Studies on Efficacy, Acceptability, Outcomes Measurement Methods, and Studies' Feasibility. Cureus. 2023 Oct 9;15(10):e46738. doi: 10.7759/cureus.46738. PMID: 38022216; PMCID: PMC10631496.&quot;&gt;US&lt;/a&gt;), both of which settled on the same three studies as their core evidence base. This is a demonstration of the unique feature of scientific data and processes – the relative independence from the observer. They didn’t have to coordinate their findings; the scientific methodology did that for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to the conclusion they concurrently came to, it’s that there are only several randomized trials on the use of cranberry products in pregnant women, and they did not show any reduction in urinary infection rates. Most trials are of poor quality, so odds are the conclusions might change if, theoretically, better studies are conducted in the future. What they did find was high dropout rates (at 30–50%), and the women reported intolerance of the high dosages of cranberry juice they were prescribed. The replacement of juice with pills helped a bit, but the dropout rates were still high – indicating that whatever benefits there may have been were accompanied by inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-research&quot;&gt;The Research:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-8e863b53-dfe0-40c3-b18a-d18d0beef039?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post was created by a team of researchers and journalists with the help of multiple generative AI tools. Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-research&quot;&gt;video bibliography&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2024-01-04-2.md&quot;&gt;Full changelog&lt;/a&gt; of this page is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The original Zheln methodology is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; about anything.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. Cranberries for Urinary Infections. Zheln. 2024 Jan  4;51(2):t5e3. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/04/2/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/28/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/11/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/04/2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/04/2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neglected Evidence About Beetroot</title>
        <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/04/2/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The International Olympic Committee recognized beetroot as a potent performance booster, among other nitrate supplements. Everybody else claims beetroot is “powerful” stuff to take before exercise. Is it? Zheln collected and appraised current research and found no ground for such optimism, even though there are data from dozens of trials that might come useful in specific contexts. Watch popular internet claims smash against evidence in this Zheln Thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video report about the &lt;em&gt;Making Of&lt;/em&gt; this post is available from &lt;a href=&quot;#written-in-stone&quot;&gt;Write in Stone&lt;/a&gt;, a research transparency platform. Also, be sure to check &lt;a href=&quot;#publication-notes&quot;&gt;Publication Notes&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about the Zheln process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#citation&quot;&gt;How to Cite This Post?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effects-of-beetroot-supplements-on-muscular-performance&quot;&gt;Effects of Beetroot Supplements on Muscular Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lots-of-studies-to-digest-on-beetroot-not-so-surprisingly&quot;&gt;Lots of Studies to Digest on Beetroot, (Not So) Surprisingly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/Z3JU7&quot;&gt;Zheln search&lt;/a&gt; located this systematic review on the effects of beetroot, first &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/27697061.2023.2211318&quot; title=&quot;Evangelista JF, Meirelles CM, Aguiar GS, Alves R, Matsuura C. Effects of Beetroot-Based Supplements on Muscular Endurance and Strength in Healthy Male Individuals: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. J Am Nutr Assoc. 2024 Jan;43(1):77-91. doi: 10.1080/27697061.2023.2211318. Epub 2023 May 11. PMID: 37167368.&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; online back in May 2023. It seemed fascinating that somebody conducted a scientific investigation centered on beetroot ingestion. However, that review only focused on muscular strength and endurance and only on healthy males, which seemed too restrictive, so I looked up more and broader reviews that focused on muscular and sports performance, exclusive of the effects beetroot has on blood pressure. Perhaps surprisingly, but whenever a new systematic review is published, it is usually the case that it is not the first one, so it is always good practice to lurk more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to focus only on those reviews that looked at randomized trials because the effects of beetroot ingestion is a pretty interventional research question, meaning that an experiment can be conducted where a group of people is divided randomly into two, with one group taking actual beetroot juice or supplements and the other one taking a placebo, and nobody knows what the heck they are taking, including any health care staff on-site. That’s a study design called a double-masked placebo-controlled randomized trial, and it’s basically the only study design that has a chance of looking remotely convincing to scientists about causality. And, it’s a commonly used study design in health research actually, so the odds of identifying such studies are pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-12-28-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;White, Superman-looking athlete, with their muscles showing from underneath the skin, holding a jar of red pills. Another jar of pills, labeled &amp;quot;Nitrates,&amp;quot; and several large beetroots lie on a table in the foreground.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of looking up individual studies ourselves, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;Zheln’s strategy&lt;/a&gt; is to make use of systematic reviews of studies already available out there. A systematic review is a sophisticated version of your regular “top 5 smartphones” or “best 10 action movies” kind of study, with a research study of a particular type as their focus of interest and a streak of comprehensiveness in them, instead of selecting the “top” or “best,” but the quality of the included studies is also considered. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epistemonikos.org/&quot;&gt;Epistemonikos&lt;/a&gt; to look up systematic reviews on beetroot. And, as a pretty illustrative case, 25 reviews mentioning “beetroot” were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epistemonikos.org/search?q=beetroot&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt;, in addition to the one from May 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reviewed all of these, and 2 additional systematic reviews were worthy of further discussion. One review looked at and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/S000711452300034X&quot; title=&quot;Afrisham R, Farrokhi V, Ghanavati M, Asbaghi O, Mohammadi S, Mohammadian M, Taghvaei-Yazdeli T, Safaei-Kooyshahi S, Jadidi Y, Ashtary-Larky D. The effects of beetroot and nitrate supplementation on body composition: a GRADE-assessed systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Nutr. 2023 Oct 28;130(8):1343-1356. doi: 10.1017/S000711452300034X. Epub 2023 Feb 27. PMID: 36847169.&quot;&gt;did not find&lt;/a&gt; any effects of ingesting beetroot or nitrates (yeah, that’s what beetroot is rich in) on body weight, fat mass, and some other body indicators. Based on the quality of the included studies, the review authors had low to moderate certainty in this conclusion (i.e., no effects found), which means more and better research could potentially challenge it in the future. The authors of the other review &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/19390211.2021.1939472&quot; title=&quot;Jones L, Bailey SJ, Rowland SN, Alsharif N, Shannon OM, Clifford T. The Effect of Nitrate-Rich Beetroot Juice on Markers of Exercise-Induced Muscle Damage: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Human Intervention Trials. J Diet Suppl. 2022;19(6):749-771. doi: 10.1080/19390211.2021.1939472. Epub 2021 Jun 21. PMID: 34151694.&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; some evidence of a small positive impact of beetroot/ nitrate supplementation on muscle recovery 2 to 3 days post-exercise but were not very certain in this conclusion, due to multiple concerns about the quality of the research they examined. Finally, let’s look at that biased review that only considered young healthy males: here they &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/27697061.2023.2211318&quot; title=&quot;Evangelista JF, Meirelles CM, Aguiar GS, Alves R, Matsuura C. Effects of Beetroot-Based Supplements on Muscular Endurance and Strength in Healthy Male Individuals: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. J Am Nutr Assoc. 2024 Jan;43(1):77-91. doi: 10.1080/27697061.2023.2211318. Epub 2023 May 11. PMID: 37167368.&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; a small positive influence of beetroot on muscular strength and endurance, and also seemed pretty certain of this finding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;international-olympic-committee-almost-got-it-right&quot;&gt;International Olympic Committee (Almost) Got It Right&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the International Olympic Committee listed beetroot under “Supplements with good to strong evidence of achieving benefits to performance when used in specific scenarios,” as a food rich in nitrates. Under “Performance impact,” they referenced 5 randomized trials and 1 &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s40279-016-0617-7&quot; title=&quot;McMahon NF, Leveritt MD, Pavey TG. The Effect of Dietary Nitrate Supplementation on Endurance Exercise Performance in Healthy Adults: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Sports Med. 2017 Apr;47(4):735-756. doi: 10.1007/s40279-016-0617-7. PMID: 27600147.&quot;&gt;additional&lt;/a&gt; systematic review. In summary, they did find some evidence of some small impacts on performance. Comparing their wording to what we saw above, I would say that their wording is close to accuracy, except that they trusted the evidence too much, not taking study quality issues into account (as also is clear from the “hierarchy of evidence” they presented), so their “good to strong evidence […] in specific scenarios” is in fact “good evidence […] in specific scenarios” at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
RCT cross-over &quot;16 male team-sport players received NO3 −-rich (BR; 140 mL day−1; 12.8 mmol of NO3 −), and NO3 −-depleted (PL; 140 mL day−1; 0.08 mmol NO3 −) beetroot juice for 7 days. On day 7 of supplementation, subjects completed the IST (two 40-min “halves” of repeated 2-min blocks consisting of a 6-s “all-out” sprint, 100-s active recovery and 20 s of rest), on a cycle ergometer during which cognitive tasks were simultaneously performed.&quot; Thompson C , Wylie LJ , Fulford J , et al . Dietary nitrate improves sprint performance and cognitive function during prolonged intermittent exercise. Eur J Appl Physiol 2015;115:1825–34.doi:10.1007/s00421-015-3166-0 CrossRefPubMedGoogle Scholar

RCT cross-over &quot;subjects were assigned in a randomised, double-blind, cross-over experimental design to receive either NO3−-rich beetroot juice (BR) or NO3−-depleted beetroot juice (PL) for 5 days. Subjects completed 24 × 6-s all-out sprints, 7 × 30-s all-out sprints, and 6 × 60-s self-paced maximal efforts on days 3, 4, and 5 of supplementation, respectively.&quot; Wylie LJ , Bailey SJ , Kelly J , et al . Influence of beetroot juice supplementation on intermittent exercise performance. Eur J Appl Physiol 2016;116:415–25.doi:10.1007/s00421-015-3296-4 Google Scholar

RCT cross-over &quot;In a randomized, placebo-controlled cross-over study, seven subjects (mean ± SD, age 21 ± 2 yr, body mass 86 ± 10 kg) completed severe-intensity step cycle tests at pedal cadences of 35 rpm and 115 rpm during separate nine-day supplementation periods with NO3−-rich beetroot juice (BR) (providing 8.4 mmol NO3−/day) and placebo (PLA).&quot; Bailey SJ , Varnham RL , DiMenna FJ , et al . Inorganic nitrate supplementation improves muscle oxygenation, O₂ uptake kinetics, and exercise tolerance at high but not low pedal rates. J Appl Physiol 2015;118:1396–405.doi:10.1152/japplphysiol.01141.2014 CrossRefPubMedGoogle Scholar

RCT cross-over &quot;In a double-blind, randomized, crossover study, 36 male team-sport players received NO3--rich (BR; 70 mL·day-1; 6.4 mmol of NO3-), and NO3--depleted (PL; 70 mL·day-1; 0.04 mmol NO3-) beetroot juice for 5 days. On day 5 of supplementation, subjects completed a series of maximal 20-m sprints followed by the Yo-Yo IR1. Cognitive tasks were completed prior to, during and immediately following the Yo-Yo IR1.&quot; Thompson C , Vanhatalo A , Jell H , et al . Dietary nitrate supplementation improves sprint and high-intensity intermittent running performance. Nitric Oxide 2016;61:55–61.doi:10.1016/j.niox.2016.10.006 Google Scholar

SR and MA of RCTs &quot;The standardised mean difference from 22 trials was 0.33 (95 % Cl 0.15–0.50), indicating a small to moderate statistically significant effect in favour of dietary NO3- supplementation in TTE performance measures (p &lt; 0.01)&quot; McMahon NF , Leveritt MD , Pavey TG . The effect of dietary nitrate supplementation on endurance exercise performance in healthy adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Sports Med 2017;47:735-756.doi:10.1007/s40279-016-0617-7 Google Scholar

RCT cross-over &quot;in a double-blind, randomized crossover design, participants ingested, three hours before the commencement of the MST, either a 7 cl ‘shot’ of BR providing ~6 mmol of nitrate, or 7cl ‘shot’ of nitrate-depleted BR (placebo, PL; providing ~0·0034 mmol of nitrate). All trials took place at the same time of the day ± 1 h, and each participant had a minimum of seven days between trials. […] There was no difference observed between PL and BR for fastest sprint time (PL, 8·27 ± 0·26 vs. BR, 8·31 ± 0·27 sec; P = 0·341) or total sprint time (PL, 87·4 ± 2·9 vs. BR, 87·5 ± 2·3 sec; P = 0·804). Based on the performance decrement calculation of RSP(4), there was no difference between trials (PL, 5·71 ± 2·61 % vs. BR, 5·31 ± 2·49 %; P = 0·334).&quot; Reynolds CME , Halpenny C , Hughes C , et al . Acute ingestion of beetroot juice does not improve repeated sprint performance in male team sport athletes. Proc Nutr Soc 2016;75:E97.doi:10.1017/S0029665116001129 Google Scholar
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that the trials under consideration in all those papers spanned a huge variety of settings, such as different sports and performance metrics, and different timelines. They were usually very small, only a dozen participants or so, which makes them hardly generalizable to an average folk. Many of the trials also employed crossover between groups, which is a delicate technique that necessitates applying sophisticated analysis methods, which some researchers eventually fail to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examining-top-google-hits-on-beetroot-good-evidence-is-not-there&quot;&gt;Examining Top Google Hits on Beetroot: Good Evidence Is Not There&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we are aware of the &lt;em&gt;status quo&lt;/em&gt; of evidence about beetroot, let’s look at what the internet has to say about it. The fun start is that one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=beetroot+gym&quot;&gt;top hits&lt;/a&gt; on Google’s “beetroot + gym” is actually a systematic review, but it did not limit inclusion to randomized trials and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9010043&quot;&gt;did not perform&lt;/a&gt; quality and certainty of evidence assessment, so shame on Google’s algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other top hits from Google are very interesting and controversial:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A blog and shop Vivo Life from January 2023 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vivolife.co.uk/blogs/news/using-beetroot-powder-before-exercise&quot;&gt;advertised&lt;/a&gt; beetroot supplements as a “powerful supplement that can benefit athletes and fitness enthusiasts.” It goes on to mention one systematic review (without including a complete reference, though, so I had to &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12970-021-00463-z&quot; title=&quot;Coggan AR, Baranauskas MN, Hinrichs RJ, Liu Z, Carter SJ. Effect of dietary nitrate on human muscle power: a systematic review and individual participant data meta-analysis. J Int Soc Sports Nutr. 2021 Oct 9;18(1):66. doi: 10.1186/s12970-021-00463-z. PMID: 34625064; PMCID: PMC8501726.&quot;&gt;guess&lt;/a&gt;), and it’s very cool because this is the first time I see this review, despite my efforts above (which just highlights how much there can be out there even on mere beetroot).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Upon examination, this review has a pretty controversial methodology, but it’s still interesting that they found slightly improved peak muscle power after beetroot supplementation. However, “an average of 5%” power increase, as cited by Vivo Life, is not substantiated by the review authors: “an ES [effect size] of this magnitude [Hedge’s G of 0.3, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statisticshowto.com/hedges-g/&quot;&gt;see an explanation here&lt;/a&gt;]–which equates to a ~ 5% increase in maximal muscle power–is likely to be of considerable athletic and clinical significance, as previously discussed,” they write. However, this statement is purely speculative, and one of the papers they cite to support it &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.niox.2014.08.014&quot;&gt;presented&lt;/a&gt; a 4% increase in the setting of a &lt;em&gt;large&lt;/em&gt; effect size anyway, not a small one that we have here, and for one particular muscle only, not for “muscle power” in general. Also, the review authors failed to account for the quality of the included studies appropriately, which led to unwarranted certainty in the conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Vivo Life authors referenced just two other sources of evidence to support their claim, both subpar reviews (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.14336/AD.2017.1207&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12061796&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;). What I am trying to say is that Vivo Life’s vigorous enthusiasm about beetroot supplements is not supported by solid scientific evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2017 article on Delish, another top hit for “beetroot + gym” on Google, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.delish.com/kitchen-tools/advice/a53773/eating-this-before-a-workout-could-improve-your-results/&quot;&gt;claims&lt;/a&gt; that beetroot will “dramatically boost your workout” (“True story: this food’s hard to beat,” goes the subtitle). They only reference that &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9010043&quot;&gt;top-hit&lt;/a&gt;, subpar review we already looked at, as well as several non-academic sources, so the claims are, clearly, pretty far from okay.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2015 article on the U.S. National Public Radio (NPR) website &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2015/10/14/448314966/why-you-might-want-to-be-drinking-beet-juice-at-the-gym&quot;&gt;suggested&lt;/a&gt; “dramatic power boosts to be gained from beet juice,” drawing extensively on only 3 trials (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCHEARTFAILURE.115.002141&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1139/apnm-2014-0228&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00372.2013&quot;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;). We have already discussed at length why relying on three trials only is completely inappropriate in this case.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Verywell Fit articles are reviewed by board-certified physicians and nutrition and exercise healthcare professionals. Medical Reviewers confirm the content is thorough and accurate, reflecting the latest evidence-based research. Content is reviewed before publication and upon substantial updates.”&lt;/em&gt; A Verywell Fit article, last updated in July 2023, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellfit.com/how-does-beet-juice-improve-athletic-performance-4123855&quot;&gt;covered&lt;/a&gt; a multitude of purported beetroot effects, so this largely falls outside of this post’s coverage, but the athletic performance section only referenced the aforementioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9010043&quot;&gt;top-hit&lt;/a&gt;, subpar review and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00421-015-3166-0&quot;&gt;1 trial&lt;/a&gt; – clearly, a poor selection of research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was running out of time, so only had a brief look at Washington Post’s 2019 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/beet-juice-gains-traction-as-an-evidence-based-aid-for-athletes/2019/03/22/8e93b1cc-45a2-11e9-90f0-0ccfeec87a61_story.html&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt; of the beetroot problem, and the sources covered did not seem to coincide much with those that we covered above. But, this was 2019, so please let me know if you reviewed in more detail and think Washington Post did a great job there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chatgpt-is-optimistic-about-beetroot-but-not-based-on-evidence&quot;&gt;ChatGPT Is Optimistic About Beetroot, But Not Based on Evidence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zheln:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;is beetroot good before exercise?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Yes, beetroot can be a beneficial food to consume before exercise. Beetroot is rich in nitrates, which the body can convert into nitric oxide. Nitric oxide helps to relax blood vessels, improve blood flow, and increase oxygen delivery to muscles. This can potentially enhance exercise performance, especially during endurance activities.

Beetroot juice or whole beets are commonly used for this purpose. Some studies suggest that consuming beetroot about 2-3 hours before exercise may be optimal for maximizing the nitric oxide benefits. However, individual responses can vary, so it's a good idea to experiment with timing and amounts to see what works best for you.

It's essential to be aware that beetroot can also have a mild laxative effect in some individuals, so it's a good idea to try it in a controlled manner before a workout to see how your body responds.

Always consider your personal preferences, tolerances, and any potential interactions with other foods or medications you may be taking. If you have specific health concerns or conditions, it's advisable to consult with a healthcare professional or a nutritionist before making significant changes to your diet.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;written-in-stone&quot;&gt;Written in Stone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-8e863b53-dfe0-40c3-b18a-d18d0beef039?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;publication-notes&quot;&gt;Publication Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The initial draft of this post was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://claude.ai/&quot;&gt;Claude 2 AI&lt;/a&gt; was completely rewritten before publication. In the interest of transparency, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2023-12-28-1.md&quot;&gt;full changelog&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The opening summary was generated by prompting &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;ChatGPT 3.5&lt;/a&gt; to “write an engaging one-sentence description for this post,” then asking it for “less drama,” and tweaking the end result a bit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The image for this post was generated with DALL·E 3 via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bing.com/images/create&quot;&gt;Microsoft Bing Image Creator Preview&lt;/a&gt; by copying and pasting the post description as a prompt. Four images will be generated, of which the most suitable was selected manually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#written-in-stone&quot;&gt;video report&lt;/a&gt; for the methodology behind the research underpinning this post. The original Zheln methodology is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This publication is a piece of volunteer research and journalism. To express support, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. Neglected Evidence About Beetroot. Zheln. 2023 Dec 28;51(1):t4e3. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/28/1/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2024/01/04/2/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;How to Stay Tuned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Instagram’s Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point of contact for &lt;strong&gt;Zheln Threads&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln’s Instagram&lt;/a&gt;. You can also easily contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; about anything. Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/28/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/28/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting Your Kid Ready for School?</title>
        <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/21/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/28/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A comprehensive review of 32 trials spanning from 1967 to 2021 reveals negligible benefits of center-based early education programs, raising questions about their effectiveness and the need for further research to inform parents and caregivers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video report about the &lt;em&gt;Making Of&lt;/em&gt; this post is available from &lt;a href=&quot;#written-in-stone&quot;&gt;Write in Stone&lt;/a&gt;, a research transparency platform. Also, be sure to check &lt;a href=&quot;#publication-notes&quot;&gt;Publication Notes&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about the Zheln process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#citation&quot;&gt;How to Cite This Post?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effects-of-early-education-on-school-readiness&quot;&gt;Effects of Early Education on School Readiness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The age of entry to school (kindergarten) varies from country to country and can be anywhere between 3 and 7 years. At this age, some kids experience difficulties starting school education, so early education centers exist that provide preschool preparation services, which are supposed to improve school readiness. Thus, this topic impacts &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbank.org/en/topic/earlychildhooddevelopment&quot;&gt;more than 100 million&lt;/a&gt; preschool children and their parents worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-12-24-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Exploring the Impact of Early Education on School Readiness&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;School readiness can be measured with a number of scales, for example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://idela-network.org/the-idela-tool/&quot;&gt;IDELA tool&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=%22Kindergarten+Readiness+Test%22+Larson&quot;&gt;Larson’s Kindergarten Readiness Test&lt;/a&gt;. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/cl2.1363&quot; title=&quot;McCartan CJ, Roberts J, Jordan JA. Centre-based early education interventions for improving school readiness: A systematic review. Campbell Syst Rev. 2023 Dec 13;19(4):e1363. doi: 10.1002/cl2.1363. PMID: 38093815; PMCID: PMC10718474.&quot;&gt;new study&lt;/a&gt;, published in December 2023, looked at trials that evaluated the effectiveness (and safety!) of early education for improving school readiness, and they identified 32 such trials. The earliest of the trials was published in 1967, and the most recent was published in 2021. Two of the studies were conducted in Canada, one in Pakistan, one in France, and the rest was done in the United States. The types of early education included “Head Start,” “Bright Beginnings,” “Creative Curriculum,” “Montessori,” “PATHS,” and “Tools of the Mind,” among others. The trials encompassed a total of almost 16,900 children and followed them up anywhere from 1 to 6 years, and here is what they found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to visiting daycare without any enriched school readiness curricula, kids who received early education did not differ in school readiness as measured by the above-mentioned standardized tests after 1 year from the start of the trials. Additionally, cognitive and physical development metrics, emotional well-being, and social skills were not different between these groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, compared to staying at home without any structured home-based education or being on a waitlist, kids who received early education only differed slightly. Curiously, the cognitive skills were only a quarter-a-point to 6.3 points higher among these children, which could advance them at most one level on the scale used (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanford%E2%80%93Binet_Intelligence_Scales&quot;&gt;Stanford–Binet Intelligence Scale&lt;/a&gt;). Emotional well-being and social skills were no different, and physical development and school readiness were not measured. Also, early education raised the probability of kids receiving a health check-up in one trial, with no information as to how useful these additional visits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers also noted that most of the current evidence is too uncertain to draw firm conclusions, due to the poor conduct of some of the trials. This means that the conclusions might change if new, better studies are conducted. The authors were moderately certain about only one piece of evidence: the lack of differences in physical development after 1 year spent at a center with enriched curricula compared to those without (1 trial involving 336 children). None of the studies looked at the potential harms of early childhood education, e.g., anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the benefits of center-based early education programs were negligible for improving school readiness, mostly studied in the U.S. setting. Even though the absence of evidence does not equal the evidence of absence, parents and caregivers should consider the lack of support for the effectiveness and no information about potential adverse effects of early childhood education after the completion of 32 trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;written-in-stone&quot;&gt;Written in Stone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-58450f68-aa70-4124-a15c-5c20b91a6d1c?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;publication-notes&quot;&gt;Publication Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The initial draft of this post was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://claude.ai/&quot;&gt;Claude 2 AI&lt;/a&gt; and then revised substantially before publication. In the interest of transparency, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2023-12-24-2.md&quot;&gt;full changelog&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The opening summary was generated by prompting &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;ChatGPT 3.5&lt;/a&gt; to “write an engaging one-sentence description for this post.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The image for this post was generated with DALL·E 3 via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bing.com/images/create&quot;&gt;Microsoft Bing Image Creator Preview&lt;/a&gt; by copying and pasting the post description as a prompt. Four images were generated, of which the most suitable was selected manually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#written-in-stone&quot;&gt;video report&lt;/a&gt; for the methodology behind the research underpinning this post. The original Zheln methodology is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This publication is a piece of volunteer research and journalism. To express support, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. Getting Your Kid Ready for School?. Zheln. 2023 Dec 24;50(2):t3e14. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/21/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/28/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;How to Stay Tuned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Instagram’s Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point of contact for &lt;strong&gt;Zheln Threads&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln’s Instagram&lt;/a&gt;. You can also easily contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; about anything. Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drugs That Can Cause Dementia</title>
        <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/07/13/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Explore the complexities of reducing medication burdens in older adults, assessing over 170 drugs, dissecting guidelines, and highlighting the current lack of evidence on patient perspectives in this crucial health issue affecting millions globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video report about the &lt;em&gt;Making Of&lt;/em&gt; this post is available from &lt;a href=&quot;#written-in-stone&quot;&gt;Write in Stone&lt;/a&gt;, a research transparency platform. Also, be sure to check &lt;a href=&quot;#publication-notes&quot;&gt;Publication Notes&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about the Zheln process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#citation&quot;&gt;How to Cite This Post?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anticholinergic-deprescribing-and-cognitive-decline-risk&quot;&gt;Anticholinergic Deprescribing and Cognitive Decline Risk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Older adults commonly take multiple drugs at once. Many of them impact a person’s cognition, as is seen, for example, in a commonly &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/02791072.2023.2251985&quot; title=&quot;Dourron HM, Copes H, Vedre-Kyanam A, Reyes DD, Gossage M, Sweat NW, Hendricks PS. A Qualitative Analysis of First-Hand Accounts of Diphenhydramine Misuse Available on YouTube. J Psychoactive Drugs. 2023 Aug 31:1-9. doi: 10.1080/02791072.2023.2251985. Epub ahead of print. PMID: 37650682.&quot;&gt;misused&lt;/a&gt; over-the-counter drug against allergies, diphenhydramine. The combined impact of such medications (that are called anticholinergic) can increase the risk of dementia and lead to other poor health outcomes. An online calculator, which was created to estimate this combined impact, features a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acbcalc.com/medicines&quot;&gt;list&lt;/a&gt; of over 170 drugs that possess these properties. Accordingly, current guidelines for health care practitioners include the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng97/chapter/Recommendations#medicines-that-may-cause-cognitive-impairment&quot;&gt;recommendation&lt;/a&gt; to try and reduce this burden when prescribing to older adults. In consequence, this topic is massively important and impacts &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/global-issues/ageing&quot;&gt;over 500 million&lt;/a&gt; older people worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-12-21-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Navigating the Maze of Anticholinergic Deprescribing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little is known about the barriers and facilitators to successfully reducing this burden. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11096-021-01293-4&quot; title=&quot;Stewart C, Gallacher K, Nakham A, Cruickshank M, Newlands R, Bond C, Myint PK, Bhattacharya D, Mair FS. Barriers and facilitators to reducing anticholinergic burden: a qualitative systematic review. Int J Clin Pharm. 2021 Dec;43(6):1451-1460. doi: 10.1007/s11096-021-01293-4. Epub 2021 Jun 25. PMID: 34173123; PMCID: PMC8642323.&quot;&gt;2021 study&lt;/a&gt; identified two studies that asked a total of 48 health care practitioners about this, and they spoke about many barriers. Importantly, but not unusually, unfortunately, no studies were identified that actually asked the patients or their carers about this problem, how they feel about it, or how they think it could be changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD015405.pub2&quot; title=&quot;Taylor-Rowan M, Alharthi AA, Noel-Storr AH, Myint PK, Stewart C, McCleery J, Quinn TJ. Anticholinergic deprescribing interventions for reducing risk of cognitive decline or dementia in older adults with and without prior cognitive impairment. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023 Dec 8;12(12):CD015405. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD015405.pub2. PMID: 38063254; PMCID: PMC10704558.&quot;&gt;new study&lt;/a&gt;, published in December 2023, reviewed the effectiveness of any measures aimed at the reduction of this kind of drug burden. Only three trials were identified, and all of them looked at medication review and changes by health care teams. However, the data reported were so poor that the researchers could draw no conclusions from it, despite the involvement of a total of almost 300 participants in these trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, anticholinergic burden is a widely recognized medical problem. Despite that, no evidence is available as to the successes of anticholinergic burden reduction. 300 participants were involved in 3 trials to test that, but the trials did not provide good evidence. No studies have looked at how patients feel about the anticholinergic drug burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;written-in-stone&quot;&gt;Written in Stone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-58450f68-aa70-4124-a15c-5c20b91a6d1c?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;publication-notes&quot;&gt;Publication Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The initial draft of this post was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://claude.ai/&quot;&gt;Claude 2 AI&lt;/a&gt; and then revised substantially before publication. In the interest of transparency, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drzhelnov/zheln.github.io/commits/master/_posts/thread/2023-12-21-1.md&quot;&gt;full changelog&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The opening summary was generated by prompting &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;ChatGPT 3.5&lt;/a&gt; to “write an engaging one-sentence description for this post” and then asking for “less drama.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The image for this post was generated with DALL·E 3 via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bing.com/images/create&quot;&gt;Microsoft Bing Image Creator Preview&lt;/a&gt; by copying and pasting the post description as a prompt. Four images were generated, of which the most suitable was selected manually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;#written-in-stone&quot;&gt;video report&lt;/a&gt; for the methodology behind the research underpinning this post. The original Zheln methodology is available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This publication is a piece of volunteer research and journalism. To express support, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhelnov P. Drugs That Can Cause Dementia. Zheln. 2023 Dec 21;50(1):t2e13. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/21/1/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/07/13/1/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/24/2/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;How to Stay Tuned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Instagram’s Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point of contact for &lt;strong&gt;Zheln Threads&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln’s Instagram&lt;/a&gt;. You can also easily contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; about anything. Donations are accepted via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/21/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/21/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Threads: #1 Neck Pain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Zhelnov P. Threads: #1 Neck Pain. A critical appraisal and evidence-dissemination assessment of &lt;em&gt;‘Hu T, Long Y, Wei L, Zheng Y, Tong Y, Yuan M, Liu C, Wang X, Lin Y, Guo Q, Huang J, Du L. The Underappreciated Placebo Effects and Responses in Randomized Controlled Trials on Neck Pain: A Systematic Review With Meta-analysis. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2023 Jul;104(7):1124-1131. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2022.10.013&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2022.10.013&lt;/a&gt;. Epub 2022 Nov 20. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.gov/36417969&quot;&gt;PMID: 36417969&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/em&gt; Zheln. 2023 Jul 13;27(1):t1e3. URI: https://zheln.com/thread/2023/07/13/1/.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/summary/2022/04/06/suppl/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/12/21/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlights&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Zheln conducted a systematic search and evidence selection based on predefined criteria.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;As a result, Zheln selected and critically appraised a recent systematic review of evidence with large social and practical importance for people suffering from neck pain and anyone involved in their care.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Evidence shows that the placebo effect is a major contributor to the treatment effect of various non-operative interventions for nonspecific neck pain (with or without neural involvement).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Despite its importance, this evidence nor the issue itself is largely not covered online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-zheln-threads&quot;&gt;Enter Zheln Threads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Zheln Threads&lt;/strong&gt; process consists of three stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence Selection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence Appraisal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence Dissemination Assessment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎉 I am excited to announce that, in order to achieve unparalleled transparency, this Zheln Threads process in its entirety is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/public/research/published-a747f353-a450-42f9-8f18-6840d444cc21&quot;&gt;Written in Stone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; width: 100%; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;top: 0; width: 100%; height: 100% !important; position: absolute&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-top-navigation allow-orientation-lock allow-scripts allow-forms&quot; src=&quot;https://www.writeinstone.com/widget/published-a747f353-a450-42f9-8f18-6840d444cc21?lightmode=false?primary=000000?secondary=5a4e70&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-selection&quot;&gt;Evidence Selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systematic review selected for appraisal:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Hu T, Long Y, Wei L, Zheng Y, Tong Y, Yuan M, Liu C, Wang X, Lin Y, Guo Q, Huang J, Du L. The Underappreciated Placebo Effects and Responses in Randomized Controlled Trials on Neck Pain: A Systematic Review With Meta-analysis. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2023 Jul;104(7):1124-1131. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2022.10.013&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2022.10.013&lt;/a&gt;. Epub 2022 Nov 20. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.gov/36417969&quot;&gt;PMID: 36417969&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zheln search and selection are based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42021224418&quot;&gt;original Zheln protocol&lt;/a&gt;. The procedure itself has evolved since the protocol publication, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/Z3JU7&quot;&gt;search query&lt;/a&gt; and the selection criteria have remained basically the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participants/population:&lt;/strong&gt; Humans. COVID-19 populations are excluded to avoid duplication of research and focus shift.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intervention(s), exposure(s):&lt;/strong&gt; Any intervention into a human life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparator(s)/control:&lt;/strong&gt; Any intervention into a human life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main outcome(s):&lt;/strong&gt; Any practice-important and question-relevant outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-appraisal&quot;&gt;Evidence Appraisal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zheln Review Appraisal in 10 Steps:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/p1m-ortho/qs-global-ortho-search-queries/blob/global-sr-query/README.md&quot;&gt;PubMed Systematic Subset&lt;/a&gt; Daily Updates&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Meets &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/11820967_Taking_Advantage_of_the_Explosion_of_Systematic_Reviews_An_Efficient_MEDLINE_Search_Strategy&quot;&gt;Shojania &amp;amp; Bero 2001&lt;/a&gt; True Positive Criteria for Systematic Reviews by Either Title or Abstract?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Full Text or Other Reports Collected by &lt;strong&gt;Zheln&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Generates Pragmatic Evidence Directly Relevant to Evidence-Based Practice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Is Not Duplicate&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Passed Reproducibility Check&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Does Not Have Critical Conduct Flaws&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Liked by &lt;strong&gt;Zheln&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Practical Implications Summarized by &lt;strong&gt;Zheln&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Appraisal Published&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The practical implication is that the placebo effect is a major contributor to the treatment effect of various non-operative interventions for nonspecific neck pain (with or without radiculopathy).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The systematic review does not appear to be duplicate at a quick glance.&lt;/strong&gt; Upon quick PubMed and Google searches, no review seems to be covering the whole of neck pain treatment with a focus on the placebo effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a similar systematic review was published recently by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1097/AJP.0000000000001092&quot;&gt;Plener et al.&lt;/a&gt;, covering only conservative treatment and only radiculopathic cervical pain. Unfortunately, it is paywalled, so I was unable to look into it and gain insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The review appears to be well-conducted overall.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors searched all the most important databases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MEDLINE (PubMed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EMBASE (Ovid)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CINAHL (EBSCO)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physiotherapy Evidence Database (PEDro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;World Health Organization International Clinical Trials Registry Platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This randomized trial by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5093/clysa2019a23&quot;&gt;Ceniza-Bordallo et al.&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2019, which I casually came across on the first page of a Google for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=neck+pain+placebo&quot;&gt;(neck pain placebo)&lt;/a&gt;, was not included in Hu’s review, and I could not check if it was in the excluded because the authors had not reported the list of exclusions. Alternatively, maybe the search strategy did not capture this trial (this trial appears not to be indexed in PubMed, and the authors only reported their PubMed strategy, so I could not check). Overall, it looks like a good search strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another relevant trial, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00404-X&quot;&gt;Jones et al.&lt;/a&gt;, has just been published and was unavailable to Hu et al. at the time of their searches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just as a remark, no trials of surgical treatments were eventually included in the Hu’s review, although those could have been eligible if had a placebo group.&lt;/strong&gt; Five randomized trials of surgery vs. non-surgery are known to me at this point, none of which includes a placebo or no-treatment group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kadanka Z, Bednarík J, Vohánka S, Vlach O, Stejskal L, Chaloupka R, Filipovicová D, Surelová D, Adamová B, Novotný O, Nemec M, Smrcka V, Urbánek I. Conservative treatment versus surgery in spondylotic cervical myelopathy: a prospective randomised study. Eur Spine J. 2000 Dec;9(6):538-44. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s005860000132&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1007/s005860000132&lt;/a&gt;. PMID: 11189924; PMCID: PMC3611417.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;With a follow-up study:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Kadaňka Z, Bednařík J, Novotný O, Urbánek I, Dušek L. Cervical spondylotic myelopathy: conservative versus surgical treatment after 10 years. Eur Spine J. 2011 Sep;20(9):1533-8. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00586-011-1811-9&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1007/s00586-011-1811-9&lt;/a&gt;. Epub 2011 Apr 26. PMID: 21519928; PMCID: PMC3175900.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Persson LC, Carlsson CA, Carlsson JY. Long-lasting cervical radicular pain managed with surgery, physiotherapy, or a cervical collar. A prospective, randomized study. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 1997 Apr 1;22(7):751-8. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1097/00007632-199704010-00007&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1097/00007632-199704010-00007&lt;/a&gt;. PMID: 9106315.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cesaroni A, Nardi PV. Plasma disc decompression for contained cervical disc herniation: a randomized, controlled trial. Eur Spine J. 2010 Mar;19(3):477-86. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00586-009-1189-0&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1007/s00586-009-1189-0&lt;/a&gt;. Epub 2009 Nov 10. PMID: 19902277; PMCID: PMC2899766.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;van Geest S, Kuijper B, Oterdoom M, van den Hout W, Brand R, Stijnen T, Assendelft P, Koes B, Jacobs W, Peul W, Vleggeert-Lankamp C. CASINO: surgical or nonsurgical treatment for cervical radiculopathy, a randomised controlled trial. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2014 Apr 14;15:129. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2474-15-129&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1186/1471-2474-15-129&lt;/a&gt;. PMID: 24731301; PMCID: PMC4012146.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taso M, Sommernes JH, Kolstad F, Sundseth J, Bjorland S, Pripp AH, Zwart JA, Brox JI. A randomised controlled trial comparing the effectiveness of surgical and nonsurgical treatment for cervical radiculopathy. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2020 Mar 16;21(1):171. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12891-020-3188-6&quot;&gt;doi: 10.1186/s12891-020-3188-6&lt;/a&gt;. PMID: 32178655; PMCID: PMC7076994.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two come from a relevant systematic review by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001466.pub3&quot;&gt;Nikolaidis et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2010). I have also found a follow-up study for Kadaňka’s trial, but I am not sure if anyone looked at its data. Cesaroni et al. was published later and then covered by the review by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00586-012-2553-z&quot;&gt;van Middelkoop et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2013). I have found the remaining trials during this research, and van Geest et al. is only a protocol, probably with no results published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pain.2013.07.022&quot;&gt;Verhagen et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2013) found 39 randomized trials of surgery for cervical conditions, but they only looked at the comparison of various surgical techniques between each other (and have not found any evidence of differences whatsoever). &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31744/einstein_journal/2022AO6567&quot;&gt;Astur et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2022) found as many as 65 systematic reviews covering surgical treatment of cervical conditions, but it is unclear how many of those also included nonrandomized trials or found any new randomized trials having a placebo or non-treatment control group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The limitations of the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; include the high risk of statistical bias in most of the trials included as well as evidence of missing data both within and across trials. All of this means that the effect estimates could be even less extreme in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the finding that the placebo effect is a major contributor to the treatment outcomes in neck pain is likely to stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-dissemination&quot;&gt;Evidence Dissemination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Summary:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Neither the review nor the underlying evidence nor the topic of placebo in neck pain have been widely discussed or disseminated online.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The current most popular resources on neck pain treatment for the general audience do not mention placebo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After looking on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=%22The+underappreciated+placebo+effects+and+responses+in+randomized+controlled+trials+on+neck+pain%3A+a+systematic+review+with+meta-analysis%22&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.altmetric.com/details/139921004&quot;&gt;Altmetric&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;I identified no coverage of the given review in any media except for Twitter so far.&lt;/strong&gt; The Twitter coverage is 30 tweets as of now, which mostly are retweets. As of now, the Altmetric score is 19, which placed the review in the top 10% of all research outputs ever tracked by Altmetric (#1,792,769 of 24,004,724 outputs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The top neck-pain-related webpages retrieved by Google did not mention placebo.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=neck+pain+treatment&quot;&gt;Google’s&lt;/a&gt; disease info snippet and &lt;em&gt;Related questions&lt;/em&gt; did not mention placebo or its contribution to the actual observed effects of the treatment for neck pain, nor did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neck_pain&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; or the websites of reputable clinics (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/neck-pain/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20375587&quot;&gt;Mayo Clinic&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/symptoms/21179-neck-pain&quot;&gt;Cleveland Clinic&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/pain/how-to-soothe-a-sore-neck&quot;&gt;Harvard Health Publishing&lt;/a&gt;), popular portals (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spine-health.com/conditions/neck-pain/treatment-neck-pain&quot;&gt;Spine-Health&lt;/a&gt;), and government authorities (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/neck-pain-and-stiff-neck/&quot;&gt;NHS&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accidentally, I came across &lt;strong&gt;links falsely claiming they lead to evidence&lt;/strong&gt; whereas in fact they do not (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/opioids-about-as-effective-as-placebo-for-lower-back-and-neck-pain-study-finds&quot;&gt;MedicalNewsToday&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sydney.edu.au/news-opinion/news/2023/06/29/opioids-no-more-effective-than-placebo-for-acute-back-and-neck-p.html&quot;&gt;The University of Sydney News&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;strong&gt;on MedicalNewsToday, some external links leading to scientific articles are marked with a tick and a label &lt;em&gt;Trusted Source&lt;/em&gt; whereas in fact the articles themselves are not checked,&lt;/strong&gt; just the journal or resource, which in itself says little about the trustworthiness of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt; (Free Research Preview. May 24 Version) did not mention the importance of the placebo effect in its overview of neck pain treatment:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;User: what is important to know for the general public about the treatment of neck pain?

ChatGPT: When it comes to the treatment of neck pain, there are several important points that the general public should be aware of:

1. Identify the cause: Neck pain can have various causes, including muscle strain, poor posture, injury, arthritis, or underlying medical conditions. It is crucial to identify the underlying cause of your neck pain to determine the most appropriate treatment.
2. Consult a healthcare professional: If you experience persistent or severe neck pain, it is advisable to consult a healthcare professional, such as a primary care physician, chiropractor, or physical therapist. They can evaluate your condition, provide a diagnosis, and recommend appropriate treatment options.
3. Rest and gentle movement: In many cases, rest and avoiding activities that worsen the pain can help alleviate neck discomfort. However, prolonged immobilization can be counterproductive. Gentle neck exercises and stretches recommended by a healthcare professional can help improve flexibility and strength, promoting healing and reducing pain.
4. Good posture: Maintaining good posture throughout the day is important for neck health. Avoid prolonged periods of slouching or craning your neck forward while using electronic devices. Ensure that your workstation is ergonomically designed to support proper posture.
5. Heat and cold therapy: Applying heat or cold therapy can provide temporary relief for neck pain. Cold packs can help reduce inflammation, while heat packs or warm showers can help relax tense muscles. Alternate between the two as needed, but avoid applying heat or cold directly to the skin to prevent burns or frostbite.
6. Over-the-counter pain relief: Non-prescription pain medications like acetaminophen (Tylenol) or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin) can be effective in reducing mild to moderate neck pain. However, always follow the recommended dosage and consult a healthcare professional if you have any concerns or existing medical conditions.
7. Physical therapy: For persistent or more severe neck pain, a healthcare professional may refer you to a physical therapist. They can provide targeted exercises, manual therapy, and other modalities to alleviate pain, improve range of motion, and strengthen the neck and supporting muscles.
8. Ergonomic adjustments: Making ergonomic adjustments to your workspace, such as using an ergonomic chair, adjusting the height of your computer monitor, and using a supportive pillow, can help reduce neck strain and promote better posture.
9. Stress management and relaxation techniques: Emotional stress and tension can contribute to neck pain. Engaging in stress management techniques such as deep breathing exercises, meditation, yoga, or other relaxation techniques can help reduce overall stress levels and alleviate neck pain.
10. Lifestyle modifications: Adopting a healthy lifestyle can contribute to overall well-being and help prevent or manage neck pain. Maintaining a balanced diet, engaging in regular physical activity, managing weight, and avoiding smoking can all promote neck health.

Remember, these points provide general guidance, but each individual's situation is unique. It's important to consult with a healthcare professional for personalized advice and treatment options based on your specific condition and medical history.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When prompted directly, ChatGPT provided a good overview of the placebo effect in general and in the treatment of neck pain in particular, without a clear focus on the contribution of the placebo effect to the actual treatment effects. As is to be expected of it, ChatGPT does not cite any sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;User: what can you tell about the placebo effect with regard to the treatment of neck pain?

ChatGPT: The placebo effect refers to the phenomenon in which a patient experiences a perceived improvement in their symptoms or condition after receiving an inactive treatment or intervention that is presented as an active treatment. In the context of neck pain, the placebo effect can play a role in the perception of pain relief and overall treatment outcomes.

Studies have shown that placebos can have a notable impact on pain management, including neck pain. When individuals believe they are receiving a genuine treatment, even if it is a placebo, their brain can release endorphins and other neurotransmitters that contribute to pain relief and a sense of well-being. This response can lead to subjective improvements in pain intensity and functional abilities.

In the specific case of neck pain, clinical trials evaluating various treatments often include a placebo control group. Participants in the control group receive an inactive treatment, such as a sugar pill or a sham procedure, while another group receives the active treatment being tested. By comparing the outcomes of the active treatment group to those of the placebo group, researchers can assess the true effectiveness of the treatment beyond the placebo effect.

Interestingly, even when participants are fully aware that they are receiving a placebo, they may still experience some level of pain relief. This suggests that psychological factors, such as the patient's belief in the treatment and the therapeutic context, can contribute to the placebo effect.

It's important to note that while the placebo effect can produce real improvements in subjective experiences, it does not address the underlying cause of the condition. It may provide temporary relief or enhance the effectiveness of other treatments, but it does not result in long-term healing or resolution of the issue.

Healthcare professionals are aware of the placebo effect and strive to distinguish true treatment effects from placebo effects when evaluating the efficacy of interventions. They use rigorous scientific methods, such as randomized controlled trials, to ensure accurate assessments of treatments and to differentiate between actual therapeutic effects and placebo responses.

In summary, the placebo effect can have a noticeable impact on the perception of pain relief and treatment outcomes in neck pain. However, it is essential to differentiate between true treatment effects and the placebo response when evaluating the effectiveness of interventions. Healthcare professionals rely on scientific research and clinical evidence to guide the selection of appropriate treatments for neck pain.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this Zheln Thread, we have seen a case study of how important health research evidence can be published and rest unused and not disseminated through the most popular media channels. Although a good systematic review has shown that the placebo effect plays a great role in how neck pain treatments are effective in the first place, popular media outlets, as of now, do not cover the role of placebo in neck pain whatsoever, leave alone the evidence from this systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, we have noticed important flaws in how popular media convey research. Particularly, we have seen how they can mislead the reader into trusting a research study whereas they only assessed the journal where the study had been published, not the study itself. In other instances, they have falsely claimed that the link leads to supporting evidence whereas, upon clicking, there is none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, important health evidence needs to be brought to daylight. Moreover, popular outlets are no longer efficient in collecting, assessing, and conveying this evidence to the general public. The explosive rise of generative artificial intelligence does not currently lead in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Zheln, we are determined to fix that. Join us on our way to building the world’s first evidence outlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-stay-tuned&quot;&gt;How to Stay Tuned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln on Instagram’s Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point of contact for &lt;strong&gt;Zheln Threads&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Zheln’s Instagram&lt;/a&gt;. You can also easily contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; about anything.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/thread/2023/07/13/1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/thread/2023/07/13/1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thread</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Future of Zheln</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Zhelnov P. The Future of Zheln. Zheln. 2022 Apr 6;Suppl:s32e2. URI: https://zheln.com/summary/2022/04/06/suppl/.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/summary/2021/10/20/suppl/&quot;&gt;« Previous Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/thread/2023/07/13/1/&quot;&gt;Next Post »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background-to-zheln&quot;&gt;Background to Zheln&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/summary/2021/10/20/suppl/&quot;&gt;Previous Summary Post&lt;/a&gt; for a &lt;strong&gt;Short Intro to Zheln.&lt;/strong&gt; Also, in that post I mentioned that Zheln was going to explore options for tackling the problem that had pushed me to its development. Namely, we do not have a single, most popular resource that every health practitioner would go to and easily retrieve the most recent and carefully examined health information for their needs. Ideally, also, the same resource should have a general audiences section, recognized as the top information provider for public health media. We have no such single best resource, no one-stop-shop option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…But probably such a monopoly is simply not possible on the market?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zheln-as-service&quot;&gt;Zheln as Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;principal method&lt;/em&gt; that Zheln was built on was searching PubMed (or, alternatively, another search platform) to continuously retrieve newly added records of systematic reviews (as well as other forms of &lt;a href=&quot;https://cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/41382.html&quot;&gt;knowledge synthesis&lt;/a&gt;). The records found were to be then categorized into medical specialties (to create updated specialty-specific listings for health care professionals), and their associated studies critically appraised to deliver accurate representation of the evidence within to health information users (both pro and general audiences).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, both the technical and business implementation of Zheln has turned out to be deficient. I was working alone, used software inefficiently, and did not manage to secure crowd funding. Also, upon closer review I have come to realize that the existing platforms flourished (as compared to Zheln, at least) and were able do deliver very similar content—we are talking about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tripdatabase.com/&quot;&gt;Trip&lt;/a&gt; database, &lt;a href=&quot;https://iloveevidence.com/&quot;&gt;L·OVE&lt;/a&gt; by Epistemonikos, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthevidence.org/&quot;&gt;Health Evidence&lt;/a&gt;, above all. Incidentally, I have also started to notice other examples of important research duplication (apart from Zheln), and this is the insight that will hopefully have grown into my PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Zheln does not appear to work as it is, or as described in its current protocol (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;DOI 10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&lt;/a&gt;) and as registered in its PROSPERO record (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?RecordID=224418&quot;&gt;CRD42021224418&lt;/a&gt;). But that alone should not mean that the &lt;em&gt;principal method&lt;/em&gt; for Zheln was wrong, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is where I introduce the concept of &lt;strong&gt;Zheln as Service.&lt;/strong&gt; An organization has contacted me to create content for their public resource for health evidence users. Well, this is exactly what I am going to do: to continue retrieving records from PubMed using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.31222/osf.io/y2nrb&quot;&gt;published Zheln methodology&lt;/a&gt; (while likely continuing to report this in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/p1m-ortho/qs-global-ortho-search-queries&quot;&gt;methods GitHub repository for Zheln&lt;/a&gt;, in the same way as before, but without publication on  &lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com&quot;&gt;Zheln.com&lt;/a&gt;), then select and appraise the records that could be of interest to my commissioner, and, finally, sell my summaries to them. I &lt;a href=&quot;https://zheln.com/summary/2021/10/20/suppl/#so-what-are-we-going-to-do-for-crying-out-loud&quot;&gt;have already said&lt;/a&gt; that I do not worry about the brand­—methods use and their impact is my only concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This what I think of as Zheln as Service. If, for any reason, you would like to try this too, you are welcome to get in touch using any of my contacts below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you then, and take care!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-in-touch&quot;&gt;How to Get in Touch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pavel@zheln.com&quot;&gt;Email Me&lt;/a&gt; about Anything&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also easily contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.me/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Telegram&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/igzheln&quot;&gt;Instagram account for Zheln&lt;/a&gt; is not currently being tracked (nor is my personal &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.com/drzhelnov&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; account).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zheln.com/summary/2022/04/06/suppl/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zheln.com/summary/2022/04/06/suppl/</guid>
        
        
        <category>summary</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
